A Guide to the Papers of Dr. James R. Sweeney, 1905-199-
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Dr. James R. Sweeney 1905-199-
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
10-4B1
6 Hollinger Document Cases. 2.5 linear feet
Sweeney, James R.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
A gift from Dr. James R. Sweeney, 1981.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. James Sweeney began teaching at Old Dominion University in 1970. It wasn't until later that year that he received his Ph.D. from the University of Notre Dame upon completing his thesis on the Harry F. Byrd political organization in Virginia.
Dr. Sweeney has taught courses on Virginia history, American Civilization, and a course on United States history since 1945. He has published articles for historical journals such as the Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, the Virginia Quarterly Review, and the Presidential Studies Quarterly. Additionally, he has written two books: Old Dominion University: A Half Century of Service in 1980, and Race, reason, and massive resistance: the diary of David J. Mays, 1954-1959 which was published in 2008.
Sweeney was the first official archivist for ODU starting in 1974, though at the time this position was only part time. Sweeney carried a 6 hour class load in addition to his archivist duties. He began working as archivist when President Bugg created the position and remained in the position until 1981. Sweeney was instrumental in establishing the University Archives and Special Collections in the ODU library in 1976. He oversaw the transition of the University Archives from scattered offices in BAL into the new Library. Before that time, University materials were unofficially collected on campus by Dr. Benjamin Clymer and Dr. Robert McClelland.
Dr. Sweeney started an oral history program in the Archives which interviewed present and former professors, staff, and students about their experiences at the college. Additionally, prominent Hampton Roads citizens were interviewed about life and organizations in the local community. This oral history program still continues in the ODU Library.
Additionally, Dr. Sweeney serves as the chapter advisor to Phi Alpha Theta, the history honor society, which publishes The Old Dominion University Historical Review. He has served as a national officer of this society.
Scope and Content
This collection includes material related to Old Dominion University and Hampton Roads history collected by Dr. James R. Sweeney, associate professor of history and former University Archivist. Included are correspondence, photos, news clippings, and oral history materials, as well as Sweeney's notes and drafts for a book he wrote in 1980 on ODU history. ODU history materials date as far back as the 1920s. Local history dates back as far as 1905.
Index Terms
Sweeney, James R.; Old Dominion University; Hampton Roads (Va.: Region); Correspondence; Clippings; Photographs
Contents List
- ODU Library and University Archives 1974-1984
  This series consists of two sub-series.
  - ODU Library 1974, 1978-1984
    This sub-series contains architectural blueprints for construction of the new Library in 1975 and the foundation plan for the Library created by Library Director, Cynthia Duncan, in 1978.
    Alphabetical
    - Architectural Plans -- ODU Library 1974 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Foundation Plan-ODU Library by Cynthia B. Duncan 1978-1984 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - University Archives 1970s
    This sub-series contains material related to Dr. Sweeney's tenure as University Archivist in the 1970s. Included are notes, information on forming an archive, a news clipping on Dr. Sweeney and the University Archives, financial reports for the archives, and information on the Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, including a paper delivered by Sweeney at the conference.
    - Accessions Policy Article -- Submitted to American Archivist (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Archives Finds New Location, Unews 1976 December 10 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Correspondence with Frederick B. Hill, Jr. 1978-1979 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Financial Reports -- Archives 1979 Sep 30 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - MARAC -- Spring Meeting (Paper delivered by Sweeney) 1976 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - MARAC -- Winter Conference (Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference) (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Notes (Box-folder 1:9)
- ODU History 1920s-1990s
  This series is broken into six sub-series related to the history of Old Dominion University.
  - Interviews 1970s-1990s
    This sub-series contains information about Oral History interviews conducted by Dr. Sweeney and others to record the oral histories of Old Dominion University. Most of this sub-series is made up of notes, correspondence, and news clippings related to the several individuals interviewed in this process. There is one transcript for a 1975 oral history interview with Lewis Webb, a past president of the college. Additionally there are examples of release forms and information on how to conduct oral histories. Most of the material is not dated, though most materials were collected or compiled in the 1970s with a few items dated as late as the 1990s.
    - Emily Williams Interview with Webb 1975 Sep 3 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - George Archibald Interview -- Notes and Correspondence (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Interview Correspondence (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Interviewee Notes I undated (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Interviewee Notes II undated (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Interviewee Notes III undated (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Interviewee Notes IV undated (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Oral History Forms undated (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Oral History Interviews undated (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Correspondence Related to the History of ODU 1920s-1960s
    Correspondence related to the history of ODU. This sub-series contains historical correspondence related to the history of ODU. Included are correspondence between the college and the Virginia Governor's office from the 1920s to the 1960s, as well as correspondence related to the college's Board of Visitors. Topics include: President Bugg's salary, funding and finances, speaking invitations, Board of Visitors appointments, becoming a 4-year college, and funding for a library building and books, as well as other buildings.
    Chronological
    - Correspondence with Virginia Governor's Office 1920s (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Correspondence with Virginia Governor's Office 1930s-1940s (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Correspondence with Virginia Governor's Office 1950s (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Correspondence with Virginia Governor's Office 1960s (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Bugg, President, Regarding His Salary 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - News Clippings 1930s-1960s
    This sub-series contains historical clippings related to the history of ODU. Included are clippings from the Norfolk Division's Silver Anniversary in 1955, clippings from the 1960s, and various non-dated clippings that appear to go back to the 1930s.
    - Norfolk Division Silver Anniversary Clippings 1955 Sep 25 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Clippings 1960s (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Notes and News Clippings for University History undated (Box-folder 2:8)
  - ODU: A Half Century of Service 1920s-1990s
    This sub-series contains material related to Dr. Sweeney's book "ODU: A Half Century of Service" published in 1980. Materials are mainly drafts and revisions of chapters in the book, but there is also a book outline and one folder of correspondence regarding promotion of the book.
    The drafts and revisions are ordered chronologically by decade covered, but everything else in this sub-series is arranged alphabetically.
    - Correspondence -- Book Promotion 1980 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History 1920s (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History 1930s (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Draft -- ODU History -- Edited Version 1930s (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History 1940s (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History 1950s (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History 1960s (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History 1970s (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History for 50th Anniversary 1980 (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Drafts -- Revisions -- ODU History 1990s (Box-folder 3:10)
    - ODU History -- Becoming an Independent Institution and University (Box-folder 3:11)
    - Outline for ODU: A Half Century of Service (Box-folder 3:12)
    - Research ODU History -- The Revolution of Distance Learning (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Other ODU Research and Notes 1920s-1990s
    This sub-series contains notes and research materials related to various topics of ODU's history. Included are athletics history, Board of Visitors minutes from the 1920s and 1930s, correspondence related to discontinuing the ROTC on campus in 1950, a compilation of documents from William T. Hodges, the Director of the Norfolk Division from 1932 to 1941, student protests and controversy in the 1960s, opening announcements for the Norfolk Division of William and Mary in 1930, the Norfolk Division of William and Mary seal, and Virginia Acts of Assembly that relate to the college. This sub-series dates from the 1920s through the 1990s.
    - Athletics History (Box-folder 4:1)
    - Athletics History -- Orange Bowl Minus One? -- ODU vs. Miami In Football (Box-folder 4:2)
    - Athletics History -- Greyson Daughtrey, 1st Track Coach at Norfolk Division (Box-folder 4:3)
    - Board of Visitors Meeting 1920-1939 (Box-folder 4:4)
    - Discontinuance of ROTC at Norfolk Division 1950 Sep 23 (Box-folder 4:5)
    - Documents Selected from the Files of Dr. W. T. Hodges 1934-1941 (Box-folder 4:6)
    - History Notes (Box-folder 4:7)
    - The Immaculate Deception, controversial article in The Gadfly 1969 (Box-folder 4:8)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Box-folder 4:9)
    - Norfolk Division of William and Mary Opening Announcements (Box-folder 4:10)
    - Norfolk Division of William and Mary Seal (Box-folder 4:11)
    - Note Cards (Box-folder 4:12)
    - Students for a Democratic Society (Box-folder 4:13)
    - Virginia Acts of Assembly Pertaining to ODU (Box-folder 4:14)
  - ODU 50th Anniversary 1976-1980
    This sub-series contains information related to the ODU 50th Anniversary committee on which Dr. Sweeney served. Included are proposals, correspondence, minutes, and timelines for this project.
    - 50th Anniversary Committee (Box-folder 4:15)
    - 50th Anniversary Correspondence (Box-folder 4:16)
    - University History Project (Box-folder 4:17)
- Local History 1905-1980s
  This series contains items related to local history, but not specifically ODU history. Topics include: Atlantic University, a university that was founded around the same time as the Norfolk Division of William and Mary. It went bankrupt shortly thereafter, but was revived in the 1980s by the Association for Research and Enlightenment; the Freelance, a Norfolk newsletter from 1905-06; Jamestown Exposition postcards from 1907; and the Norfolk Gorilla, a 1970s radical newspaper.
  - Atlantic University undated (Box-folder 4:18)
  - The Freelance 1905-1906 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Jamestown Exposition Postcards 1907 (Box-folder 4:20)
  - The Norfolk Gorilla 1971 (Box-folder 4:21)
- Florence "Fay" Zetlin 1950s-1970s
  Fay Zetlin was a well-known Virginia artist who also taught in the Art Department at ODU. This series is broken into two sub-series.
  - Correspondence 1950s-1970s
    Correspondence dates from the 1950s to the 1970s and mainly concerns exhibitions of her work.
    - Correspondence 1950s (Box-folder 4:22)
    - Correspondence 1960s (Box-folder 4:23)
    - Correspondence 1970s (Box-folder 4:24)
    - Correspondence undated (Box-folder 4:25)
  - News Clippings 1950s-1970s
    News clippings date from the 1950s to the 1970s and are primarily related to exhibitions of her work.
    - News Clippings 1950s (Box-folder 4:26)
    - News Clippings 1960s (Box-folder 4:27)
    - News Clippings 1970s (Box-folder 4:28)
    - News Clippings undated (Box-folder 4:29)
- Photos 1920s-1980s
  This series contains a complete set of ODU 50th Anniversary photos. Additionally, there are a few photos that are not a part of this set. This sub-series is broken into 11 sub-series. All photos except those in sub-series L. are from the 50th Anniversary photo set.
  - Athletics and Sports
    This sub-series contains photos of athletics and sports. Included are: archery, baseball, men's and women's basketball, cheerleading, football, and sailing.
    - Archery -- Women's (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Baseball (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Basketball -- Men's (Box-folder 5:3)
    - Basketball -- Women's (Box-folder 5:4)
    - Cheerleading (Box-folder 5:5)
    - Football (Box-folder 5:6)
    - Sailing (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Buildings and Grounds
    This sub-series contains photos of campus buildings and grounds. Included are: Batten Arts and Letters (BAL), Webb Center, Canterbury House, Foreman Field, the Old Larchmont School and the Old School of Education Building, the Technical Institute, and campus construction.
    - Batten Arts and Letters (BAL) (Box-folder 5:8)
    - Building at Night (Box-folder 5:9)
    - Canterbury House (Box-folder 5:10)
    - Construction (Box-folder 5:11)
    - Foreman Field (Box-folder 5:12)
    - Old Larchmont School (Box-folder 5:13)
    - Old School of Education Building (Box-folder 5:14)
    - Technical Institute (Box-folder 5:15)
    - Webb Center (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Faculty and Staff 1920s-1980s
    This sub-series contains photos of individual faculty and staff members from Academic Counseling and Testing, the Administration Office, the Business Department; Campus Police, the Library, the Physics Department, the Social Studies Division, and the Technical Institute. Also included are past Presidents of the college, and faculty events.
    - Academic Counseling and Testing -- Walter Earl and Kathleen Doub (Box-folder 5:17)
    - Administration Staff (Box-folder 5:18)
    - Business -- Dean Diener 1980 (Box-folder 5:19)
    - Campus Police 1979 (Box-folder 5:20)
    - Chandler, Alvin Duke (Box-folder 5:21)
    - Faculty Frolics 1968 (Box-folder 5:22)
    - Library Staff (Box-folder 5:23)
    - Physics Staff (Box-folder 5:24)
    - Rollins, Alfred, ODU President 1976-1985 (Box-folder 5:25)
    - Social Studies Division -- Dr. Stanley Pliska, Dr. Warren F. Spencer, Dr. W. J. Schell (Box-folder 5:26)
    - Technical Institute - Dr. Lee M. Klinefelter (Box-folder 5:27)
    - Unknown Meeting (Box-folder 5:28)
    - Unknown Staff (Box-folder 5:29)
    - Webb, Lewis, ODU President 1962-1969 (Box-folder 5:30)
  - Freshmen
    This sub-series contains photos of freshmen and freshmen events.
    - Freshmen Bowing to Upperclassmen (Box-folder 5:31)
    - Freshman Cake Race (Box-folder 5:32)
  - Greek Life 1950s-1960s
    This sub-series contains photos of fraternities and sororities including Circle K, IMPS, Pi Phi Sigma, and Tiga, as well as Greek events such as Greek Week and the Cotillion Rush Party.
    - Circle K (Box-folder 5:33)
    - Cotillion Rush Party 1954 (Box-folder 5:34)
    - Greek Week 1965 May 10-15 (Box-folder 5:35)
    - IMPS 1960s (Box-folder 5:36)
    - Pi Phi Sigma (Box-folder 5:37)
    - Tiga 1961 April (Box-folder 5:38)
  - Music and Entertainment undated, 1963
    This sub-series contains photos of musical and theatrical events, including a concert of Peter, Paul, and Mary in 1963.
    - Music (Box-folder 5:39)
    - Opera (Box-folder 5:40)
    - Peter, Paul, and Mary Concert 1963 Apr 28 (Box-folder 5:41)
    - Theater (Box-folder 5:42)
  - Prominent Personalities undated, 1972
    This sub-series contains photos of famous people, political figures, and prominent citizens. Of note, is a photo of Ernest Hemingway with Professor William Seward.
    - Attorney General Albertis Harrison, Jr. and Senator Mills Godwin, Jr. (Box-folder 5:43)
    - Charles Kaufman and Albertis Harrison with Lewis Web (Box-folder 5:44)
    - Ernest Hemingway and William Seward (Box-folder 5:45)
    - Senator Mark Hatfield of Oregon 1972 Feb 9 (Box-folder 5:46)
  - Publications
    This sub-series contains photos of people holding the Chieftain and the High Hat.
    - The Chieftain (Box-folder 5:47)
    - The High Hat (Box-folder 5:48)
  - Seniors and Graduation 1920s-1960s
    This sub-series contains photos of seniors, graduating classes, senior officers, and various graduation ceremonies.
    - Colgate W. Darden, Jr. Commencement Speaker 1954 June 7 (Box-folder 6:1)
    - Convocation 1943 May 15 (Box-folder 6:2)
    - First Graduating Class (Box-folder 6:3)
    - Senior Class Officers 1969 (Box-folder 6:4)
    - Senior Class Ring 1956 (Box-folder 6:5)
    - Various Graduation Photos (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Student Life
    This sub-series contains photos of a variety of themes that represent the life of students at the college.
    - Alumni (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Dining (Box-folder 6:8)
    - Dorm Antics (Box-folder 6:9)
    - Events -- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 6:10)
    - Groups of Students (Box-folder 6:11)
    - Events -- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 6:10)
    - Groups of Students (Box-folder 6:11)
    - Military / ROTC (Box-folder 6:12)
    - Physical Education (Box-folder 6:13)
    - Politics (Box-folder 6:14)
    - Protests (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Streakers (Box-folder 6:16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 6:17)
  - Miscellaneous
    This sub-series contains miscellaneous photos.
    - Antarctica Research (Box-folder 6:18)
    - Christmas Tree (Box-folder 6:19)
    - Madison Cleaners Car (Box-folder 6:20)
    - Red Cross (Box-folder 6:21)
    - Signs and Seals (Box-folder 6:22)
    - William and Mary -- VPI Norfolk Division Car (Box-folder 6:23)
    - Women War Workers (Box-folder 6:24)
  - Other Photos (not 50th Anniversary)
    This sub-series contains photos that are not a part of the ODU 50th Anniversary set.
    - Photo Material relating to president of ODU Dr. James L. Bugg, Jr. (Box-folder 6:25)
    - Vet's Club Plaque Photo (Box-folder 6:26)